<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="building_and_publishing_using_github_actions">
    <title>Building, Validating, and Publishing Using GitHub Actions</title>
    <prolog>
        <author>Radu Coravu</author>
        <critdates>
            <created date="2024-01-23"/>
        </critdates>
    </prolog>
    <conbody>
        <p>If you have a GitHub-hosted DITA XML project (either on a private or public repository),
            you can define GitHub actions to validate and publish your DITA XML project. </p>
        <p>As an example, the Oxygen XML Blog contains GitHub actions to validate and publish a DITA
            XML project:<ul id="ul_mj4_j5t_21c">
                <li>Publish the Oxygen XML Blog DITA XML project to <b>Netlify</b> using a
                        <b>GitHub</b> action:<ol id="ul_jhk_qwt_21c">
                        <li>Create an account on <xref href="https://www.netlify.com/" format="html"
                                scope="external">Netlify</xref> and create a site for the account.
                            Create an <xref
                                href="https://app.netlify.com/user/applications#personal-access-tokens"
                                format="html" scope="external">authentication token</xref> to be
                            able to access Netlify from a command line and deploy to the site from a
                            remote location. In the Netlify UI, obtain the ID of <xref
                                href="https://app.netlify.com/sites/oxygenxmlblog/configuration/general#site-information"
                                format="html" scope="external">your site</xref>.</li>
                        <li>In the GitHub project's <b>Settings->Secrets and variables->Actions</b>
                            category, define two variables to keep the Netlify authentication token
                            and the side ID values. Also, create a secret for the <b>Oxygen
                                Publishing Engine</b> license key.</li>
                        <li>Create a custom <xref
                                href="https://github.com/oxygenxml/blog/blob/master/build/build.gradle"
                                format="gradle" scope="external">Gradle build file</xref> that
                            downloads the <b>Oxygen Publishing Engine</b>, licenses it, produces the
                            output, and stores it in a specific folder.</li>
                        <li>Create a custom <xref
                                href="https://github.com/oxygenxml/blog/blob/master/.github/workflows/publish.yml"
                                format="yml" scope="external">GitHub action</xref> that runs the
                            build file and then uses a plugin to upload the entire folder to the
                            Netlify web site. The end result looks like this: <xref
                                href="https://oxygenxmlblog.netlify.app/" format="html"
                                scope="external"/>.</li>
                    </ol></li>
                <li>Validate the entire DITA project using the Oxygen <xref
                        href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/doc/ug-editor/topics/scripting_oxygen_dita_validate_and_check_for_completeness.html"
                        format="html" scope="external"><b>Validate and Check for
                        Completeness</b></xref> command line script:<ol id="ul_xzd_n5t_21c">
                        <li>In the GitHub project's <b>Settings->Secrets and variables->Actions</b>
                            category, define a variable named <codeph>SCRIPTING_LICENSE_KEY</codeph>
                            that has the Oxygen scripting license key as its value.</li>
                        <li>Set up a <xref
                                href="https://github.com/oxygenxml/blog/blob/master/build/build-validate-check.gradle"
                                format="gradle" scope="external">Gradle build file</xref> that
                            downloads an Oxygen all platforms kit, licenses it, and runs it over the
                            DITA map. The build file also applies an XSLT stylesheet over the XML
                            report to produce a Markdown report.</li>
                        <li>Create a <xref
                                href="https://github.com/oxygenxml/blog/blob/master/.github/workflows/validate-check-completion.yml"
                                format="yml" scope="external">GitHub action</xref> that is triggered
                            by pull requests or modifications done to pull requests, sets up Java,
                            calls the Gradle build file, and then if there are errors, outputs the
                            report in Markdown format using the <xref
                                href="https://docs.github.com/en/actions/using-workflows/workflow-commands-for-github-actions#adding-a-job-summary"
                                format="html" scope="external"
                                ><codeph>$GITHUB_STEP_SUMMARY</codeph></xref> variable. The report
                            of running such a GitHub action contains the severity, description, and
                            a link to the topic where the error was found. The link can be followed
                            to open the topic in Oxygen XML <b>Web Author</b>:<fig
                                id="fig_dcp_3wt_21c">
                                <image href="../images/validation-report-gh-actions.png"
                                    id="image_zf4_nvt_21c" scale="40"/>
                            </fig></li>
                    </ol></li>
                <li>Validate only the changed topics in a pull request using <b>OpenAI</b> and a
                    custom prompt to check for grammar problems:<ol id="ul_u2m_rvt_21c">
                        <li>In the GitHub project's <b>Settings->Secrets and variables->Actions</b>
                            category, define a variable named <codeph>AI_LICENSE_KEY</codeph> that
                            has the <b>OpenAI</b> key as its value.</li>
                        <li>Create a custom <xref
                                href="https://github.com/oxygenxml/blog/blob/master/build/build-validate-ai.gradle"
                                format="gradle" scope="external">Gradle build file</xref> that finds
                            all changed topics in the pull request and then uses the API key to send
                            the content to <b>OpenAI</b> asking for a report of changes in
                                <b>Markdown</b> format.</li>
                        <li>Create a <xref
                                href="https://github.com/oxygenxml/blog/blob/master/.github/workflows/ai-checks.yml"
                                format="yml" scope="external">custom GitHub action</xref> that saves
                            the list of changed files as an environmental variable and passes this
                            information to the build file, afterwards displaying the report using
                            the <codeph>$GITHUB_STEP_SUMMARY</codeph> variable. The report of
                            running such a GitHub action looks like this: <fig id="fig_pjb_mwt_21c">
                                <image href="../images/validate-ai-gh-action.png"
                                    id="image_kg3_nwt_21c" scale="40"/>
                            </fig></li>
                    </ol></li>
            </ul></p>
    </conbody>
</concept>
