<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="release_branches">
    <title>Release Branches</title>
    <prolog>
        <author>Chris Papademetrious</author>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>My name is Chris Papademetrious and I work for Synopsys Inc., a semicoductor design
            automation software company. I am an occasional guest contributor to the Oxygen XML
            blog, and I wanted to share how we use Git.</p>
        <p>Our team writes documentation for many different products. And for the most part, all
            products follow a common software and documentation release schedule (every three
            months). Our technical writers are knowledgeable on the products they write for, but
            they tend to be novices with Git.</p>
        <section id="section_znt_gvn_xwb">
            <title>Our Attempt at the Centralized Workflow</title>
            <p>When we first adopted DITA and Git, we used the centralized workflow. However, we ran
                into issues when a particular product group needed to delay their release schedule.
                When the rest of the group began working on the next release in the main branch, the
                delayed group could not stay in the main branch because then "last-release" and
                "next-release" content would get mixed and there was no single point where the main
                branch represented the final release state. And so in these cases, we had to fork a
                release branch off the main branch and move the delayed product writers there. (And
                sometimes writers would keep working in the main branch out of inertia, and so the
                main branch content would get mixed up anyway...)</p>
            <image href="../images/release_branches/snps_centralized_workflow.png" placement="break"
                id="image_hys_yzt_xwb"/>
            <draft-comment><xref
                    href="https://mermaid.live/edit#pako:eNqdU01PwzAM_SuVz-3UJs2S9cYG4sSJG-rFtO6H6JeyVGJM--9kGx2gjWgjl8jv2X7Pkr2FrM8JEihr86hxqNLOsy-rKHvrR-O1WHdfUN-2tfHqPPFSKAjNqOkuiFJw0cxNczcdT_Srxi6rPE0N4ZqiCzUTFWT278YhBc9g-ZM5SV032tI92vJ7tN_mmKuG32hiFZzbvkYnPhuf3azM_qVc1B02N6m3pEu6ovfKvS2rv7aFu2ou2z0JgQ_WnvWa2wvZ7rEUTEUtpbBPz6nAsTH77J1NxdH0z5sug8TokXwYhxwN3ddYamwncMDupe9tWGCzPsaQbOEdkiCKhZhFSoRCiQWXwoeNRWU440ywOV9IGYpQqp0PH4cObBbFXKgFZ1IpyYSaT5oPeW16PUnSIXo63vnh3HefTkhBvg"
                    format="html" scope="external"/></draft-comment>
            <p>We considered using the feature branch workflow. However, this would require writers
                to be responsible for branch actions (forking feature branches and submitting pull
                requests), which they had never done before. Many products have multiple writers,
                which would require those feature branches to be synchronized on the server for
                collaboration. Some products have 40+ features in a release cycle, and our past
                experiences told us that writers could sometimes forget to switch branches. And so
                we decided not to use this workflow.</p>
            <p>We needed a workflow in which a writer could simply continue to write for a release
                and not worry about switching branches until the release was done—<i>regardless of
                    whether their product finished its release early or late</i>. So, we moved to a
                    <term>release branch</term> workflow.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="section_iq4_fvn_xwb">
            <title>The Release Branch Workflow</title>
        </section>
        <section id="section_iq4_fwn_rwb">
            <p>In our release branch workflow, we create a branch for each release, named by the
                scheduled release date. A writer can work in a release branch as long as they like,
                and they can move to the next release branch whenever they are ready. If a feature
                requires collaboration by multiple writers, they can collaborate in that release
                branch.</p>
            <p>The key feature of our release branch workflow is the <term>cascaded release
                    merge</term>. Each week, we merge new commit activity forward from earlier
                release branches to later release branches. If a branch has no new commit activity
                since the last merge, no merge is performed from it.</p>
            <image href="../images/release_branches/snps_release_branch_workflow.png"
                placement="break" id="image_grn_f15_xwb"/>
            <draft-comment author="chrispy"><xref
                    href="https://mermaid.live/edit#pako:eNqdlE1vgzAMhv8K8plWkJBCua3btNN22W3KJQMD0Qqp0iC1Q_z30fChaSqtBjfbPHltx04DiUoRYsiledHiUPDK6b5PLaqkcDTuURyRXHNSXvXupMDkS9VmDPiDW5WlNI5MY4dDhsLUGh9WPoc5jsxzu577N0UG6i9E56HHQepOliXqHKeKhyOsczZTeoUkv0mysDf0juL1MsmijgaLtKYMF3aGznfmpu5stjdnNJOnRVWyu_c3PzXB4qmxquBejFLItFvl5oJwMAWWyOHyY4qZqPeGg9uHpmXvos1wM9DR1c6u-JsYwaldNruWV22nJGqj3s9VArHRNbpQH1Jh8EmKXItydB5E9aFUZ2Zif-xtiBs4QbzyA8bWfsQ8FrEtDZkL584bemtKGNnQbRh6zAuj1oVvewJZ-wFl0ZaSMIpCwqLNqPmcSqP0KInWeu3fM_ustT826JCe"
                    format="html" scope="external"/></draft-comment>
            <p>In the preceding diagram, the release1 branch is completed and quiet. Product writers
                are finishing work in the release2 branch and moving to the release3 branch. Their
                work in the release2 branch is automatically propagated to release3. At some point,
                a product team finds that a retroactive documentation fix is needed for a feature in
                the release1 branch. This fix is automatically propagated forward into the release2
                and release3 branches.</p>
            <p>In this workflow, the writer must remember only to check out the next release branch
                after they complete their current release. And this is a notable enough
                accomplishment that they tend to remember to do this.</p>
            <p>However, writers can work in multiple release branches if they want to. Most products
                have major releases on every third release interval. In this case, writers can make
                minor typo fixes and rewordings in the next minor release branch, but get an early
                start on feature documentation in the next major release branch. (Although in this
                case, the writers must be diligent again about remembering to switch branches!)</p>
            <p>For the most part, writers don't need to worry about the logistics of the release
                merges. However, there are some cases in which they do need to be aware of them. For
                example,</p>
            <ul id="ul_tpk_syt_xwb">
                <li>If a writer writes content for one release and wants to incrementally modify
                    that content for the next release, they must wait for the merge to propagate the
                    work forward to the next branch to be able to continue work on it.</li>
                <li>If a writer wants to add content that should not propagate forward to subsequent
                    releases (such as a temporary bug or limitation that is fixed in the next
                    release), then they add content to the earlier release, wait for a merge, then
                    remove it in the next release.</li>
            </ul>
            <p> In these cases, the writers can ask me to run a merge manually so they do not have
                to wait.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="section_c33_qb4_xwb">
            <title>The Branch-Merging Perl Script</title>
            <p>The release branch merge is performed by a perl script called
                    <filepath>merge_repo.pl</filepath>. The usage is as follows:</p>
            <pre id="pre_s4h_vb4_xwb">$ <userinput>merge_repo.pl --help</userinput>
Usage:
      --dry-run
           Do not actually commit any changes
      --starting-at branch_name
           Start merging at this branching (merging from previous branch)</pre>
            <p>The script uses the command-line <codeph>git</codeph> client to perform its work. One
                notable requirement is that the script needs a local repository to perform its
                merging work in. The script automatically fetches and pulls all remote updates,
                creating new local branches and deleting local branches that no longer have matching
                remote branches as needed.</p>
            <p>The script obtains the chronological list of release branches by querying and sorting
                all branches that match <codeph>release/*</codeph> - there is no need to update any
                branch list text files or databases as new release branches are created.</p>
            <p>Here is an example of its output:</p>
            <pre id="pre_lk3_2wt_xwb">$ <userinput>merge_repo.pl</userinput>
Checking for commits to merge from 'release/2022.09' to 'release/2022.12'...
Merging 1 commits from 'release/2022.09' to 'release/2022.12'...
Pushing merge to 'release/2022.12' upstream...
Merge from 'release/2022.09' to 'release/2022.12' succeeded.

Checking for commits to merge from 'release/2022.12' to 'release/2023.03'...
Merging 4 commits from 'release/2022.12' to 'release/2023.03'...
Pushing merge to 'release/2023.03' upstream...
Merge from 'release/2022.12' to 'release/2023.03' succeeded.

Checking for commits to merge from 'release/2023.03' to 'release/2023.06'...
Merging 8 commits from 'release/2023.03' to 'release/2023.06'...
Pushing merge to 'release/2023.06' upstream...
Merge from 'release/2023.03' to 'release/2023.06' succeeded.</pre>
            <p>Here is the resulting commit graph as shown on the Gitlab server web page, from the
                previous merge to the just-completed merge:</p>
            <image href="../images/release_branches/gitlab_merge_graph.png" placement="break"
                id="image_jlh_nwt_xwb"/>
            <p>As mentioned earlier, no matter how many "earlier" branches exist, no forward merge
                is performed from a branch unless it contains new activity since the last merge.</p>
            <p>If a release merge result cannot be pushed (perhaps because a writer just pushed
                something new to the server), the script abort its current merge, updates its local
                repository, and retries the merge.</p>
            <p>If the script encounters a merge conflict, it prints information to STDERR about how
                to manually reproduce and resolve the conflict, then continue the merge:</p>
            <pre id="pre_vjv_2xt_xwb">$ <userinput>merge_repo.pl</userinput>
Checking for commits to merge from 'release/2022.09' to 'release/2022.12'...
Merging 1 commits from 'release/2022.09' to 'release/2022.12'...
Pushing merge to 'release/2022.12' upstream...
Merge from 'release/2022.09' to 'release/2022.12' succeeded.

Checking for commits to merge from 'release/2022.12' to 'release/2023.03'...
Merging 4 commits from 'release/2022.12' to 'release/2023.03'...
Merge from 'release/2022.12' to 'release/2023.03' failed:
Auto-merging some_topic.dita
CONFLICT (content): Merge conflict in some_topic.dita
Automatic merge failed; fix conflicts and then commit the result.
some_topic.dita:21: leftover conflict marker
some_topic.dita:24: leftover conflict marker
some_topic.dita:25: leftover conflict marker
some_topic.dita:27: leftover conflict marker

Perform the following commands manually:

git checkout release/2023.03
git merge release/2022.12
...resolve conflict...
git push
merge_repo.pl --starting-at release/2023.06</pre>
            <p>The script runs every Wednesday as a <filepath>cron</filepath> job. For conflicts or
                other errors (like server downtime), the resulting output to STDERR causes
                    <filepath>cron</filepath> to email the command output to the script owner (in
                this case, me). Thanks to this behavior of <filepath>cron</filepath>, the script
                operates quietly unless attention is needed.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
